Guide to the James Fenimore Cooper Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
660 Box 13, folder 336
661 Box 11, folder 310
662 Box 11, folder 311
663 Box 13, folder 337
665 Box 13, folders 338-339
666 Box 13, folder 340
667 Box 13, folder 342
668 Box 4, folder 90
669 Box 13, 343
670 Box 11, folder 312
671 Box 13, folder 348
672 Boz 13, folder 360
673 Box 11, folder 313
674 Box 12, folders 322-323
675 Box 13, folder 363
676 Box 11, folder 295; box 13, folder 364
678 Box 11, folder 296; box 12, folder 318
679 Box 13, folder 344
680 Box 6, folder 165-167
681 Box 12, folder 325
682 Box 11, folder 314; box 13, folder 345, 365, 372
683 Box 11, folder 297; box 12, folder 315
684 Box 12, folder 316
685 Box 13, folder 376
686 Box 13, folder 366
688 Box 13, folder 347
689 Box 11, folder 298; box 13, folder 367, 373,380
690 Box 12, folder 319
691 Box 12, folder 320
692 Box 12, folder 321
693 Box 9, folders 257-259
695 Box 21, folder 469
696 Box 12, folders 322-323
697 Box 9, folder 266
698 Box 3, folder 67
699 Box 5, folder 147
702 Box 8, folder 236
703 Box 8, folder 230
704 Box 9, folder 262
705 Box 13, folder 379
706 Box 11, folder 309
708 Box 13, folder 377
709 Box 12, folders 322-323
710 Box 9, folder 270
711 Box 3, folder 62
713 Box 6, folder 150
714 Box 21, folder 470-471
715 Box 18, folder 416-427
716 Box 18, folder 416-427
717 Box 18, folder 416-427
718 Box 3, folders 73-74; box 19, folder 437
801 Box 26, folder 512
802 Box 22, folder 472
803 Box 12, folders 322-323
804 Box 27, folders 519-523
805 Box 13, folder 348
806 Box 12, folder 326
807 Box 12, folders 322-323
808 Box 13, folder 348
810 Box 13, folder 348
811 Box 11, folder 300
812 Box 13, folder 354, 357
814 Box 13, folder 351
817 Box 13, folder 361-362, 369; box 22, folder 472
818 Box 29, folders 531-532
819 Box 18, folder 415
821 Box 10, folder 277
822 Box 3, folder 103
823 Box 8, folder 220
824 Box 2, folders 34-36
825 Box 2, folders 34-36
826 Box 17, folder 392
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Correspondence; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Diaries; Novelists, American -- 19th century; Travelers' writings, American; United States -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Diaries -- United States -- 19th century; Engravings (prints) -- United States -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century; Barnard, Daniel D. (Daniel Dewey), 1797-1861; Beard, James Franklin, 1919-1989; Bentley, Richard, 1794-1871; Bradish, Luther, 1783-1863; Cooper family; Cooper, James Fenimore, 1789-1851; Cooper, James Fenimore, 1789-1851 -- Correspondence; Cooper, James Fenimore, 1789-1851 -- Diaries; Cooper, James Fenimore, 1789-1851 -- Travel -- England; Cooper, James Fenimore, 1858-1938; Cooper, Susan Fenimore, 1813-1894; De Lancey, William Heathcote, 1797-1865; Dering, Charles T.; Fagan, J. (John); Gosselin, Charles, 1795-1859; Greenough, Horatio, 1805-1852; Jay, John, 1745-1829; Jay, Peter A. (Peter Augustus), 1776-1843; Jay, William, 1789-1858; Ingersoll, Charles Jared, 1782-1862; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Myers, Ned, approximately 1793-1849; Ogden, James De Peyster, 1790-1870; Putnam, George Palmer, 1814-1872; Rives, William C. (William Cabell), 1793-1868; Shubrick, William Branford, 1790-1874; Wilkes, Charles, 1798-1877; Carey & Lea; Duncker & Humblot; Stringer & Townsend; United States. Navy ( Officers); Wiley & Putnam
- Correspondence, 1813-1894; Series I; 5.42; (13 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into three subseries: General Correspondence; Family Correspondence; and Third Party Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  The series documents Cooper's personal relationships and professional life, ranging from various ventures to his writing career and work as the American consul in Lyons, France.
  Correspondence between Cooper and his publishers, most notably Richard Bentley in England and Carey & Lea in the U.S., and his stereotyper, John Fagan, provide insight into the publishing process. The costs and processes involved in printing during the nineteenth century, discussions on copyright and the issue of piracy, and concerns about marketing and sales, are well represented in this correspondence. Cooper's relationships with publishers Lea & Blanchard, Stringer & Townsend, and G. P. Putnam are also represented, though to a lesser degree.
  Cooper's experiences while living in Europe between 1826 and 1833 can be found, for example, in his correspondence with the Marquis de Lafayette and William Cabell Rives (who was serving as minister to France). While living in Europe Cooper also worked with European publishers such as Charles Gosselin in Paris and Duncker & Humblot in Berlin.
  Cooper's involvement with, and interest in, the navy is captured in his correspondence, including his friendships with prominent naval officers William Branford Shubrick and Charles Wilkes, as well as Ned Myers (on whom Cooper based Ned Myers: A Life Before the Mast ). Cooper's correspondence with a number of naval officers who served as resources for The History of the Navy of the United States of America can be found under this title in Writings (Series II).
  A number of Cooper's acquaintances were prominent lawyers and government officials, including Daniel D. Barnard, Charles Jared Ingersoll, Joseph Reed Ingersoll, and John Jay (and his sons Peter A. and William). Cooper's friends also included Samuel F. B. Morse, merchant James de Peyster Ogden, and Charles T. Dering, with whom Cooper briefly entered the whaling business. Cooper also paid into several ventures with his niece's husband, Horace H. Comstock, who founded Comstock (Michigan) and who was originally from Cooperstown.
  Letters regarding the election of Cooper to various societies, requesting Cooper to lecture, requesting autographs, and various invitations can be found at the end of General Correspondence subseries.
  The Family Correspondence subseries contains correspondence Cooper sent to his immediate and extended family and correspondence sent between family members. Correspondence sent to Cooper from family members – family names include Cooper, De Lancey, Phinney, and Pomeroy – can be found in the General Correspondence subseries.
  The Third-Party Correspondence subseries is comprised of letters which could not be associated with material in the subseries above.
  - General Correspondence
    Related Archival Materials note
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    - "A" General, 1832-1846 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Akin, David Kelley, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      1 ALS
    - Alger, Horatio, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "B" General, 1828-1851 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Baldwin, Thomas, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      2 ALS
    - Balmanno, Robert, 1848-1851 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bancroft, George, 1845-1850 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      2 ALS to Cooper and 1 ALS from Cooper
    - Barclay, George, 1847-1850 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Barnard, Daniel D. (Daniel Dewey), 1839-1850 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      7 ALS
    - Barnet, C.W., 1828, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Barnet, I. Cox, 1827, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Baudry, 1826-1831, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      3 ALS
    - Bernard, General, 1831-1832 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bentley, Richard, 1832-1851 (Box 1, Folder 14-21)
      64 ALS to Cooper and 156 ALS from Cooper
      Includes portrait engraving
    - Berthoud, Louisa, 1838-1849 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bolton, W.C., 1844-1849 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      5 ALS
    - Borg de Balzan, G., 1842-1846 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      4 ALS
    - Boss, Nicholas G., 1830 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      1 ALS from Cooper
      Letter also addressed to DeWolf, Bayley, Clark, and Ellery
    - Bourne, Reverend Edward, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Bousquet, Archille, 1826-1827 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      6 ALS
    - Bradish, Luther, 1826-1827 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      2 ALS to Cooper and 2 ALS from Cooper
      Includes copy of letter from Luther Bradish to Carey & Lea (Publishers) and their response
    - Bradlee, Josiah, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Brevoort, Henry, 1841, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
      1 ALS to Cooper and 1 ALS from Cooper
    - Brown, James, 1826-1833 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      2 ALS; includes 1 ALS from Brown to to W.A. Barnet
    - Bryant, William Cullen, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "C" General, 1817-1851 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Carey & Lea (Publishers), 1825-1845 (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
      70 ALS to Cooper 3 ALS from Cooper
    - Carter, Samuel, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Chapman, J. G. (John Gadsby), 1830-1837 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Chauncy, Isaac, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      Includes letter from Chauncey to James Biddle
    - Chlopicki, Louis, 1838-1841 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Chodzéko, Léonard, 1831-1834 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Cicognani, Francesco Leopoldo, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      1 ALS to A. Hammett (U.S. Consul at Naples)
      Includes application to the Roman government for permission for James Fenimore Cooper to bring his traveling carriage to Rome by sea free of duty
    - Cist, Lewis J. (Lewis Jacob), 1842 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Clapp, James, 1835-1844 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Clark, Gaylord, 1838-1847 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      6 ALS to Cooper and 1 ALS from Cooper
      Includes translation in the handwriting of Anne Charlotte Fenimore Cooper of letter sent to James Fenimore Cooper by Prince Dmitri Ivanovitch Dolgorouki
    - Clinch, Charles P. (Charles Powell), 1845 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Clymer, Mary S., 1851-1852 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Coles, Benjamin N., 1822 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Includes letters to Coles from John Miller and John Murray
    - Collet, James, 1826 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Comstock, Horace H., 1835-1848 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      36 ALS
    - Cone, Salmon G., 1849 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Conner, David, 1841 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Cooper, Anne Charlotte Fenimore, 1822-1850 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Includes letters to other family members
    - Cooper, Benjamin, 1820-1829 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Cooper, Elisabeth, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Cooper, George, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Cooper, Isaac C., 1827-1847, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Cooper, I. Morris, 1840-1849 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      Includes letter to Anne Charlotte Fenimore Cooper
    - Cooper, Maria Frances Fenimore, 1819-1851 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      Includes letters to her brother James Fenimore Cooper and sister-in-law Mrs. James Fenimore Cooper
    - Cooper, Paul Fenimore, 1839-1850 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      12 ALS to his father and 1 ALS to unnamed correspondent describing his father's physical condition (1851)
      Includes miscellaneous ALS and notes in his handwriting
    - Cooper, Richard, 1835-1851 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      13 ALS
    - Cooper, Samuel, 1834-1847 (Box 3, Folder 62)
      Includes one note to Simon Buel
    - Cooper, Susan De Lancey, 1813-1850 (Box 3, Folder 63)
      12 ALS
    - Cooper, Susan Fenimore, 1848-1850 (Box 3, Folder 64)
      2 ALS and manuscript, written by James Fenimore Cooper and signed by Susan Fenimore Cooper and Frances Fenimore Cooper, transferring copyright of Susan's book Rural Hours to her father (1850)
    - Cooper, William, 1837-1847 (Box 3, Folder 65)
      9 ALS
      Includes letters to Ann Cooper Pomeroy and Susan Fenimore Cooper
    - Copway, George, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Corbin, Francis P., undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Cruger, H.N., 1830 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Cruger, Henry D., 1837-1851 (Box 3, Folder 69)
      14 ALS
    - "D" General, 1820-1850 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Davezac, A. (Auguste), 1840-1841 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Day, Thomas D., 1846-1847 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - De Kay, James E. (James Ellsworth), 1829-1846, undated (Box 3, Folder 73-74)
      7 ALS to Cooper and 2 ALS from Cooper
    - De Lancey, Caroline, 1831-1849 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      3 ALS from Cooper to De Lancey
    - De Lancey, Edward, 1848-1851 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - De Lancey, John Peter, 1814-1819 (Box 3, Folder 77)
      4 ANS
    - De Lancey, Martha, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 78)
      1 ANS to De Lancey
    - De Lancey, Thomas, 1811-1819 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - De Lancey, William Heathcote, 1828-1856 (Box 3, Folder 80)
      6 ALS from De Lancey and 3 ANS to De Lancey
    - Denio, Hiram, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Dering, Charles T., 1818-1848 (Box 3, Folder 82)
      34 ALS
    - Desmond, Daniel I., 1834 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - DeWitt, Richard Varick, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Dix, John A. (John Adams), 1840-1849 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Dobbins, Daniel, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Duff, William H., 1839-1841, undated (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Dunlap, John A., 1839-1849 (Box 3, Folder 88)
      7 ANS
    - Dunlap, William, 1831-1839 (Box 4, Folder 89)
      15 ALS
    - Duncker & Humblot, 1829-1831 (Box 4, Folder 90)
      6 ALS to Cooper
    - "E" General (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Eigenbrodt, William E., 1845-1848 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Ellet, E. F. (Elizabeth Fries), undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Elliott, Jesse D. (Jesse Duncan), 1840-1846 (Box 4, Folder 94-95)
      Includes letters to Cooper from Frances C. Elliott and Washington LaFayette Elliott
    - "F" General, 1816-1847 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Fagan, J. (John), 1843-1851 (Box 4, Folder 97)
      46 ALS to Cooper 2 ALS from Cooper
    - Field, Thomas W. (Thomas Warren), 1842-1848 (Box 4, Folder 98)
      3 ALS to Cooper 1 TL copy from Cooper
    - Fish, Hamilton, 1842-1845 (Box 4, Folder 99)
      2 ALS to Cooper
    - Flügel, J. G. (Johann Gottfried), 1830, 1845 (Box 4, Folder 100-101)
    - Foot, Lyman, 1841 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Fournier, M., undated (Box 4, Folder 103)
      1 ANS
    - Francis, John W. (John Wakefield), 1845-1851 (Box 4, Folder 104)
      4 ALS and 1 ANS to Cooper. Also includes ALS to Rufus Wilmot Griswold on the life and character of Cooper and ALS from J. Hunt, Jr. with a printed copy of a letter from Cooper to Hunt from Cincinnati "Gazette"; letters from P.E. Johnson to Francis
    - Frey, S. C., 1844 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Frye, William Edward, 1846-1847 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - "G" General, 1835-1850 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Galitizin, Princess Elizabeth, circa 1827 (Box 4, Folder 108)
      8 ALS
    - Gameye, S. E., 1839 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Gayarré, Charles, 1846-1847 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Goodrich, S. G., 1834 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Gosselin, Charles, 1826-1833 (Box 4, Folder 112)
      24 ALS
      Includes ALS sent by Gosselin to Madame Welles
    - Graham, George R., 1846 (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Greenough, Horatio, 1830-1839 (Box 5, Folder 114)
      24 ALS to Cooper, ANS to Cooper introducing Colonel A. P. Hayne, and ALS fragment to Cooper
    - Griswold, Rufus Wilmot, 1842-1851 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Grosart, Alexander Balloch, 1847 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - "H" General, 1833-1851, undated (Box 5, Folder 117-118)
    - Hackett, James Henry, 1845-1850 (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Hall, S. C. (Samuel Carter), undated (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Hammett, Alexander, 1829, 1836 (Box 5, Folder 121)
      2 ALS, enclosing copy of letter by Hammett to Francis Key
    - Hammond, Jabez D. (Jabez Delano), 1837, 1842 (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Hand, Geo. E. (George E.), 1844-1847 (Box 5, Folder 123)
      11 ALS to Cooper and 1 ALS from Cooper
    - Handy, Charles O., 1835-1836 (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Hare, Robert, 1840 (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Harvey, Jacob, 1827-1848 (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Henry Colburn and Richard Bentley (Firm), 1830-1832 (Box 5, Folder 127-128)
      29 ALS to Cooper and 27 ALS from Cooper
    - Hoffman, Benjamin, 1842 (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - Howe, Samuel Gridley, 1832 (Box 5, Folder 130)
      7 ALS to le Général de Lafayette and Cooper
    - Hunt, J. M., 1843-1845 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Hunter, Robert R., 1831 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Ingersoll, C., 1851 (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - Ingersoll, Charles Jared, 1841-1842 (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Ingersoll, Joseph Reed, 1844-1847 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Ingraham, Edward D., 1839 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Irving, Theodore, 1848 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Irving, Washington, 1850 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Ivy, Thomas J., 1848 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - "J" General, 1841-1845, undated (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Jay, John, 1837-1850 (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Jay, Mary Rutherford, 1827-1832 (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Jay, Peter A. (Peter Augustus), 1830-1845 (Box 5, Folder 143-144)
      9 ALS to Cooper and 4 ALS from Cooper
    - Jay, William, 1813-1843 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Johnston, Thomas B., 1844-1845, 1849 (Box 5, Folder 146)
      3 ALS to Cooper and 1 ALS from Cooper
    - Jones, M. M., 1840 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Jullien, [?], 1826-1837 (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - "K" General, 1814-1846 (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - Kalussowski, Henry, 1840-1841 (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - Kniasiewicz, General, 1831-1836 (Box 6, Folder 151)
    - "L" General, 1815-1850 (Box 6, Folder 152)
    - L'Advocat, C., 1832 (Box 6, Folder 153)
    - Lafayette, Georges Washington Louis Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1838 (Box 6, Folder 154)
      1 ALS and fragment of ANS to Cooper
    - Lafayette, Mme. Georges, circa 1831 (Box 6, Folder 155)
    - Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, marquis de, 1826-1834 (Box 6, Folder 156-159)
      35 AL to Cooper, 3 of which are in the hand of his secretary, 7 letters are signed (includes photostatic copies of letters)
      1 ANS from Cooper
      Miscellaneous material concerning dinner given by Americans to Lafayette in Paris
    - Lea & Blanchard, 1840-1844 (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Le National, 1831 (Box 6, Folder 161)
      1 ALS from Cooper to the editor
    - Livingston, Edward, 1829 (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - Loomis, Pascal, 1850-1851 (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Lunt, Henry, 1843-1846 (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - "M" General, 1814-1850 (Box 6, Folder 165-167)
    - McNally, W. R., 1834-1847 (Box 6, Folder 168)
    - Marlay, Elizabeth, 1832, undated (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - Matthews, Cornelius (editor of Arcturus ), 1841 (Box 6, Folder 170)
    - Mayer, Brantz, 1844-1851 (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - Miller, John, 1823-1827 (Box 7, Folder 172)
    - Moore, Francis, 1826-1827 (Box 7, Folder 173)
      4 ALS to Cooper, including 8 pages with addresses, 1 ALS from Cooper
    - Morris, George F., 1848 (Box 7, Folder 174)
    - Morris, Jacob, 1816-1844 (Box 7, Folder 175)
      5 ALS to Cooper and 1 ALS from Cooper
    - Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1832-1850 (Box 7, Folder 176)
      12 ALS to Cooper, printed circular with presentation inscription from the "Po'keepsie Telegraph," and manuscript copy of ALS from Cooper
    - Mulchinock, William P., 1850-1851 (Box 7, Folder 177)
    - Myers, Ned, 1843-1849 (Box 7, Folder 178)
      11 ALS
    - Mygatt, Henry R., 1845 (Box 7, Folder 179)
    - "N" General, 1822-1850 (Box 7, Folder 180)
    - Noble, Louis Legrand, 1848-1851 (Box 7, Folder 181)
    - "O" General, 1848-1849 (Box 7, Folder 182)
    - Oakley, J., 1847-1848 (Box 7, Folder 183)
    - Ogden, James De Peyster, 1837-1848 (Box 7, Folder 184-186)
      38 ALS
    - Omaley, M., 1833-1835 (Box 7, Folder 187)
    - Ombrosi, James, 1829-1830, undated (Box 7, Folder 188)
    - Onderdonk, Benjamin Treadwell, 1839 (Box 7, Folder 189)
    - Onderdonk, Henry, 1848-1849 (Box 7, Folder 190)
    - O'Sullivan, John Louis, 1837-1842 (Box 7, Folder 191)
    - "P" General, 1828-1850 (Box 7, Folder 192-193)
    - Packett, John, 1818 (Box 7, Folder 194)
      Statement to Cooper
    - Paulding, James Kirke, 1838-1846 (Box 7, Folder 195)
      4 ALS to Cooper and 1 ALS from Cooper
    - Pell, Anna, 1850 (Box 7, Folder 196)
    - Pell, Duncan, 1834-1850 (Box 7, Folder 197)
    - Perry, Matthew Calbraith, 1824-1839 (Box 7, Folder 198)
    - Phinney, Henry Frederick, 1843-1851 (Box 7, Folder 199)
      3 ALS, 1 memorandum to Cooper, 2 ANS from Cooper
    - Platt, Charles T., 1842 (Box 7, Folder 200)
    - Poe, Edgar Allan, 1836 (Box 7, Folder 201)
      Copy of ALS to Cooper
    - Pomeroy, Ann Cooper, 1833-1851, undated (Box 7, Folder 202)
      3 ALS and 1 ANS to Cooper and 2 ALS from Cooper
    - Post, Israel, 1837 (Box 7, Folder 203)
    - Powell, Thomas, 1849-1850 (Box 7, Folder 204)
    - Powers, James T., 1848 (Box 7, Folder 205)
    - Preble, George Henry, 1842-1850 (Box 7, Folder 206)
    - Putnam, George Palmer, 1849-1851 (Box 7, Folder 207)
      18 ALS, with sketch of map, memorandum of agreement for publication of a new work of fiction
    - "R" General, 1817-1850 (Box 8, Folder 208)
    - Randall, Henry S., 1843 (Box 8, Folder 209-210)
    - Ransom, Joseph, 1841-1849 (Box 8, Folder 211)
    - Rives, William C. (William Cabell), 1831-1832 (Box 8, Folder 212)
      17 ALS
    - Roberts, George, 1841-1842 (Box 8, Folder 213)
    - Roberts, [?], 1841 (Box 8, Folder 214)
      ALS from Cooper
    - Russell, Elizabeth Anne, 1830-1833, undated (Box 8, Folder 215)
    - "S" General, 1816-1850 (Box 8, Folder 216-218)
    - Seward, William Henry, 1849 (Box 8, Folder 219)
    - Sharp, Richard, circa 1828 (Box 8, Folder 220)
    - Shubrick, Harriet Cordelia Wethered, 1837 (Box 8, Folder 221)
    - Shubrick, Mary, undated (Box 8, Folder 222)
      ANS
    - Shubrick, William Branford, 1823-1851 (Box 8, Folder 223-229)
      95 ALS
    - Silliman, Benjamin, 1827-1831 (Box 8, Folder 230)
      1 ALS to Cooper and photostatic copy of ALS from Cooper
    - Simms, William Gilmore, circa 1844 (Box 8, Folder 231)
    - Smith, John, II, 1849-1850 (Box 8, Folder 232)
    - Spencer, John Canfield, 1843-1850 (Box 8, Folder 233)
    - Stellwagen, Henry S., 1849 (Box 8, Folder 234)
    - Sterling, Micah, 1834 (Box 8, Folder 235)
    - Stevens, L. N., 1832 (Box 8, Folder 236)
    - Stevenson, James, 1823-1850 (Box 9, Folder 237)
    - Stockdale, John Joseph, 1835 (Box 9, Folder 238)
    - Stone, William L. (William Leete), undated (Box 9, Folder 239)
    - "The Stranger", 1849 (Box 9, Folder 240)
    - Stringer & Townsend, 1847-1851 (Box 9, Folder 241)
      10 ALS
    - Sue, Eugène, undated (Box 9, Folder 242)
    - Sutherland, Jacob, 1822-1843 (Box 9, Folder 243)
    - de Syon, F. Alph., undated (Box 9, Folder 244)
      3 ANS and 5 ALS in French
    - "T" General, 1815-1850 (Box 9, Folder 245)
    - Tanski, J., 1838-1845 (Box 9, Folder 246)
    - Taylor, Charles Benjamin, 1851 (Box 9, Folder 247)
    - Taylor, Janette ["Niece, and nearest relation of John Paul Jones..."], 1843 (Box 9, Folder 248)
    - Thomas Cowperthwaite & Company, 1842-1845 (Box 9, Folder 249)
    - Troskolaski, Joseph, 1834-1842 (Box 9, Folder 250)
    - Upson, Anson, 1848 (Box 9, Folder 251)
    - Vail, Aaron, 1835 (Box 9, Folder 252)
    - Van Vechten, W., 1849 (Box 9, Folder 253)
    - Van Wagenen, G. G., 1846-1847 (Box 9, Folder 254)
    - Vassigne, Camille de, undated (Box 9, Folder 255)
    - Villermont, C. A. de, 1826-1828 (Box 9, Folder 256)
    - "W" General, 1824-1850 (Box 9, Folder 257-259)
    - Wagstaff, Dr., 1827 (Box 9, Folder 260)
    - Ward, Charles D., 1854 (Box 9, Folder 261)
    - Warren, John E., 1846 (Box 9, Folder 262)
    - Welles & Co., 1828-1834 (Box 9, Folder 263)
    - Wessells, Henry Walton, 1848-1849 (Box 9, Folder 264)
    - White, Thomas W., 1833-1836 (Box 9, Folder 265)
    - Wilkes, Charles, 1823-1850 (Box 9, Folder 266)
      17 ALS to Cooper and 2 AL from Cooper
    - Wiley & Putnam, 1839-circa 1849 (Box 9, Folder 267)
      5 ALS and 3 statements
    - Wiley, John, 1839 (Box 9, Folder 268)
    - Williams, Samuel, 1841-1844 (Box 9, Folder 269)
    - Wood, William, 1851 (Box 9, Folder 270)
      1 ALS to Cooper, also includes ALS from Lawrence McNamee to John Coller
    - Wool, John Ellis, 1845-1848 (Box 10, Folder 271)
    - Worth, G. A., 1838-1839 (Box 10, Folder 272)
    - Invitations to Cooper, 1826-1851, undated (Box 10, Folder 273-274)